<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<DEITIES>
	<DEITY>
		<NAME>
			Boccob: God of Magic
		</NAME>
		<DOMAIN>
			Knowledge, Magic, Trickery
		</DOMAIN>
		<ALIGNMENT>
			True Neutral
		</ALIGNMENT>
		<DESCRIPTION>
			Boccob is the god of magic, arcane knowledge, balance, and foresight. He is known as the Uncaring, the Lord of All Magic, and the Archmage of the Deities. All times and places are open to him, and he has visited many alternate realities and planes unknown to the wisest of sages, places even the Elder Evils avoid. His symbol is an eye in a pentagon; usually this is worn as an amulet. Boccob is usually portrayed as a middle aged man with white hair who wears purple robes decorated with golden runes. He is described as carrying the very first staff of the magi with him at all times. In addition, he knows every spell ever created and can travel to any time and dimension. He is the possessor of the only magical library that contains a copy of every potion, spell, and magic item in existence
		</DESCRIPTION>
		<FAVOREDWEAPON>Quarterstaff</FAVOREDWEAPON></DEITY>
		<DEITY>
		<NAME>
			Corellon Larethian: God of the Elves
		</NAME>
		<DOMAIN>
			Chaos, Good, Protection, War
		</DOMAIN>
		<ALIGNMENT>
			Chaotic Good
		</ALIGNMENT>
		<DESCRIPTION>
			Corellon Larethian is the leader of the elven pantheon, and the god of Magic, Music, Arts, Crafts, Poetry, and Warfare. Corellon desires to protect and preserve the elven race, return to his people their lost artistic heritage, and to thwart the schemes of the drow and the orcs. This also means guarding against the corruption within that resulted in the creation of the drow. Corellon advises his faithful to guard against stagnation as well, continually seeking out new experiences. They seek to bring out beauty through art, craft, and magic. His symbol is a crescent moon. Corellon lives in the realm of Arvandor on the plane of Arborea. Also called Arvanaith in its role as the elven afterlife, Arvandor is said to have been taken from the gods of the giants after a lengthy war. Ruins of giant citadels still dot the land there. The elven gods are thought to have invaded from the plane of Ysgard, hungry for a realm of their own. The realm is a place of deep forests and fey beauty. Corellon dwells in a magnificent tower of marble in the center of the realm. In Elven, it is called Gwyllachaightaeryll, the Many-Splendored. The art that decorates the tower's many rooms is constantly changing. Only the central throne room is a constant.
		</DESCRIPTION>
		<FAVOREDWEAPON>Longsword</FAVOREDWEAPON>
		</DEITY>
	<DEITY>
		<NAME>
			Ehlonna: Goddess of the Woodlands
		</NAME>
		<DOMAIN>
			Animal, Good, Plant, Sun
		</DOMAIN>
		<ALIGNMENT>
			Neutral Good
		</ALIGNMENT>
		<DESCRIPTION>
			Ehlonna is the goddess of Forests, Woodlands, Flora, Fauna, and Fertility. Ehlonna is known to the elves as "Ehlenestra." Her holy symbol is a rampant unicorn or a unicorn's horn. Ehlonna is variously depicted as an elven or human woman, and often associates with unicorns and other sylvan creatures. Deep within the Beastlands layer of Krigala is the Grove of the Unicorns, a realm she shares with the like-minded goddess Mielikki. Ehlonna teaches that the animals and plants of the forests are gifts, and are not to be stolen. She is often the goddess of rangers and druids and opposes hunters and anyone who would exploit the land for fun or profit.
		</DESCRIPTION>
		<FAVOREDWEAPON>Longbow</FAVOREDWEAPON>
	</DEITY>
	<DEITY>
		<NAME>
			Erythnul: God of Slaughter
		</NAME>
		<DOMAIN>
			Chaos, Evil, Trickery, War
		</DOMAIN>
		<ALIGNMENT>
			Chaotic Evil
		</ALIGNMENT>
		<DESCRIPTION>
			Erythnul is the Oeridian god of hate, envy, malice, panic, ugliness, and slaughter. He is known as the Many, and is worshipped by many gnoll, troll, ogre, and bugbear tribes, in addition to humans. His symbol is a red blood drop, or a bestial mask representing Erythnul's changing visage. Erythnul is called the Many, because in battle his features continually shift from human to bugbear to troll to ogre to gnoll and back to human again. His spilled blood transforms into similar creatures. Erythnul delights in panic and slaughter. He can spread fear through his eyes
		</DESCRIPTION>
		<FAVOREDWEAPON>Morningstar</FAVOREDWEAPON>
	</DEITY>
	<DEITY>
		<NAME>
			Fharlanghn: God of Roads
		</NAME>
		<DOMAIN>
			Luck, Protection, Travel
		</DOMAIN>
		<ALIGNMENT>
			True Neutral
		</ALIGNMENT>
		<DESCRIPTION>
			Fharlanghn, the Dweller on the Horizon, is the Oeridian god of Horizons, Distance, Travel, and Roads. He is a well-known deity on the world of Oerth. He wanders that world in person, his petitioners present in spirit form at crossroads and in mysterious oases. His symbol is a disk with a curved line representing the horizon, and an upturned crescent above that. He is the brother of Celestian, and is said to make his home on Oerth. Fharlanghn appears as an elderly man. His skin is wrinkled and weathered, but his green eyes sparkle with life. He wears unremarkable, travel-stained clothing of leather and unbleached linen. He carries the Oerth Disc, a magical version of his holy symbol. Fharlanghn insists that everyone travel in order to discover and learn new things. He urges people to look to the horizon for inspiration.
		</DESCRIPTION>
		<FAVOREDWEAPON>Quarterstaff</FAVOREDWEAPON>
	</DEITY>
	<DEITY>
		<NAME>
			Garl Glittergold: God of the Gnomes
		</NAME>
		<DOMAIN>
			Good, Protection, Trickery
		</DOMAIN>
		<ALIGNMENT>
			Neutral Good
		</ALIGNMENT>
		<DESCRIPTION>
			Garl Glittergold is the patron deity of gnomes. Garl, as god of Luck and Trickery, leads the gnomish pantheon. He is the arch enemy of kobolds and their patron deity Kurtulmak. Garl lives in the gnomish realm of the Golden Hills on the plane of Bytopia. The Golden Hills are a set of seven hills, one for each of the deities who dwell there. The whole realm glows with a golden hue. Garl's hill is known as Glitterhome, but he prefers to wander throughout the realm, often in disguise. His symbol is a gold nugget. Garl carries an intelligent axe named Arumdina.
		</DESCRIPTION>
		<FAVOREDWEAPON>Battleaxe</FAVOREDWEAPON>
	</DEITY>
	<DEITY>
		<NAME>
			Gruumsh: Chief God of the Orcs
		</NAME>
		<DOMAIN>
			Chaos, Evil, Strength, War
		</DOMAIN>
		<ALIGNMENT>
			Chaotic Evil
		</ALIGNMENT>
		<DESCRIPTION>
			Gruumsh', also known as Gruumsh One-Eye, is the patron deity of orcs, who regard him as the god of Conquest, Survival, Strength, and Territory. According to Unearthed Arcana, Gruumsh created the orcs in his image to be his servants in the world but was cheated out of a home for his people by the other gods. He is also considered a member of the default pantheon of deities. His symbol is an unblinking eye, or his missing unwinking eye. Gruumsh appears as a powerful orc with one eye. A figure of fury and driven cruelty, Gruumsh rules his pantheon with brute power. His favored weapon is the spear.
		</DESCRIPTION>
		<FAVOREDWEAPON>Spear</FAVOREDWEAPON>
	</DEITY>
	<DEITY>
		<NAME>
			Heironeous: God of Valor
		</NAME>
		<DOMAIN>
			Good, Law, War
		</DOMAIN>
		<ALIGNMENT>
			Lawful Good
		</ALIGNMENT>
		<DESCRIPTION>
			Heironeous is the Oeridian god of Chivalry, Justice, Honor, War, Daring, and Valor. His holy symbol is a silver lightning bolt, often clutched in a fist. Heironeous appears as a tall human man in a full robe of chainmail so fine that it moves with him like cloth. He has auburn hair and skin the color of copper, and is impervious to all but the mightiest weapons due to a secret solution known as meersalm. His signature weapon is a great magical battleaxe, though he has recently taken to the longsword. Heironeous sees the world as a deadly place, filled with perpetual challenges and trials for those who battle for justice and defend the weak and innocent. His followers should always act with honor and chivalry, and to uphold justice. Danger is to be faced head-on, with calm and resolve. Those who defeat evil are rewarded with Glory, while those who uphold the tenets of the Arch-paladin are rewarded with Virtue. The Arch-paladin's teachings have been codified in a chivalric code known as the Heironean Code.
		</DESCRIPTION>
		<FAVOREDWEAPON>Longsword</FAVOREDWEAPON>
	</DEITY>
	<DEITY>
		<NAME>
			Hextor: God of Tyranny
		</NAME>
		<DOMAIN>
			Destruction, Evil, Law, War
		</DOMAIN>
		<ALIGNMENT>
			Lawful Evil
		</ALIGNMENT>
		<DESCRIPTION>
			 Hextor is the Oeridian god of war, discord, massacres, conflict, fitness, and tyranny.The symbol worn and used by the followers of Hextor is a black, spiked gauntlet holding spiked arrows. Hextor is often depicted as a hideous, gray skinned, six-armed humanoid bearing two large tusks jutting from its lower jaw wearing armor clad with skulls. He wields a weapon in each hand: a spiked flail, a battle axe, a battle pick, a longsword, a mace, and a falchion. His other form is that of an athletic young male, with dark hair and light skin. The church of Hextor teaches that the world is a harsh, unforgiving place. The strong rule the weak, and power is the only reward worth having. Cruelty and mercilessness are necessary tools. Order must be forged from Chaos and law from anarchy, but order is meaningless without the will to enforce it. Tyrants are to be obeyed, and dissenters are to be oppressed or killed. Slaves must obey their masters.
		</DESCRIPTION>
		<FAVOREDWEAPON>Flail</FAVOREDWEAPON>
	</DEITY>
	<DEITY>
		<NAME>
			Kord: God of Strength
		</NAME>
		<DOMAIN>
			Chaos, Good, Luck, Strength
		</DOMAIN>
		<ALIGNMENT>
			Chaotic Good
		</ALIGNMENT>
		<DESCRIPTION>
			Kord is the Suel god of Athletics, Sports, Storms, Brawling, Strength, and Courage. His symbol is an eight-pointed star composed of spears and maces. Kord is depicted as a hugely muscular man with a red beard and long red hair. He wears a fighting girdle made from a red dragon's hide, gauntlets from a white dragon's hide, and boots from a blue dragon's hide. He wields the greatsword Kelmar in battle. Kord is sometimes depicted by his urbanized faithful as a more civilized athlete or wrestler. “The strong and fit should lead the weaker. Bravery is the greatest quality in any ruler. Scorn cowardice.”
		</DESCRIPTION>
		<FAVOREDWEAPON>Greatsword</FAVOREDWEAPON>
	</DEITY>
	<DEITY>
		<NAME>
			Moradin: God of the Dwarves
		</NAME>
		<DOMAIN>
			Earth, Good, Law, Protection
		</DOMAIN>
		<ALIGNMENT>
			Lawful Good
		</ALIGNMENT>
		<DESCRIPTION>
			Moradin is the chief deity in the dwarven pantheon. Moradin's domains are Creation, Earth, Good, Law, and Protection. His titles include Soul Forger, Dwarffather, the All-Father, and the Creator. He created the first dwarves out of earthen materials and tutored them in dwarven ways. Moradin charges his followers with the task of removing the kingdoms of orcs and wiping out the followers of Gruumsh. He is upset if they flee from their foes or kill their fellow dwarves. Moradin is worshipped at forges and hearths. Melted metals are sacrificed to him monthly.
		</DESCRIPTION>
		<FAVOREDWEAPON>Warhammer</FAVOREDWEAPON>
	</DEITY>
	<DEITY>
		<NAME>
			Nerull: God of Death
		</NAME>
		<DOMAIN>
			Death, Evil, Trickery
		</DOMAIN>
		<ALIGNMENT>
			Neutral Evil
		</ALIGNMENT>
		<DESCRIPTION>
			 Nerull is the Flan god of death, darkness, murder, and the underworld. He is known as the Reaper, the Foe of All Good, the Hater of Life, and the Bringer of Darkness. His symbol is a skull and scythe. Nerull is usually seen as a black-robed skeleton, with a rust-red body and green, ropy hair. He carries a staff called "Lifecutter" that at his command grows a scythe blade made of scarlet energy. His alignment is Neutral Evil. Nerull is the patron deity of those who seek the greatest evil for their own enjoyment or gain. Nerull's faithful believe they will be rewarded for acts of murder, for every living thing is an abomination in the eyes of the Reaper.
		</DESCRIPTION>
		<FAVOREDWEAPON>Scythe</FAVOREDWEAPON>
	</DEITY>
	<DEITY>
		<NAME>
			Obad-Hai: God of Nature
		</NAME>
		<DOMAIN>
			Air, Animal, Earth, Fire, Plant, Water
		</DOMAIN>
		<ALIGNMENT>
			True Neutral
		</ALIGNMENT>
		<DESCRIPTION>
			 Obad-Hai is the god of Nature, Woodlands, Hunting, and Beasts, one of the most ancient known. He is often called the Shalm. He is also considered to be the god of summer by the Flan. Originally a Flan deity, Obad-Hai is most favored by Rangers, druids and other nature priests. His holy symbol is a mask of oak leaves and acorns.  He can appear as a lean and weathered old man of indeterminate age, dressed in brown or russet and carrying a hornwood staff, or he can appear as a dwarf, gnome, or halfling. He can also assume the form of a centaur, pixie, satyr, sprite, treant, or in the form of various animals. Obad-hai loves nature and wilderness. He is a patron of druids and a friend to those who dwell in harmony with their natural surroundings. Characters or creatures who despoil or wantonly harm either animal or vegetable life are his foes.
		</DESCRIPTION>
		<FAVOREDWEAPON>Quarterstaff</FAVOREDWEAPON>
	</DEITY>
	<DEITY>
		<NAME>
			Olidammara: God of Rogues
		</NAME>
		<DOMAIN>
			Chaos, Luck, Trickery
		</DOMAIN>
		<ALIGNMENT>
			Chaotic Neutral
		</ALIGNMENT>
		<DESCRIPTION>
			Olidammara is the god of Music, Revels, Wine, Rogues, Humor, and Tricks. He is often called the Laughing Rogue. Olidammara is one of the more eccentric gods of Oerth. The Laughing Rogue is often involved in good-natured schemes involving the other gods (less good-natured for the more evil deities), with repercussions that can make life difficult for his faithful. He has few proper priests, but is held in high regard in almost all non-evil regions of the Flanaess. His home plane is Ysgard. His realm, on the border with Limbo, is called the Den of Olidammara. His holy symbol is a grinning mask. Other symbols of his faith include the kantele and the number nine. Olidammara teaches his followers to avoid predictability and routine, to delight in wine, to learn music, to seek out happiness, joy, entertainment, and the company of others. Olidammara advises his faithful to appreciate both the jokes they play and the jokes played on them. He also teaches that misery, temperance, and solemnity are the greatest poisons to the soul
		</DESCRIPTION>
		<FAVOREDWEAPON>Rapier</FAVOREDWEAPON>
	</DEITY>
	<DEITY>
		<NAME>
			Pelor: God of the Sun
		</NAME>
		<DOMAIN>
			Good, Healing, Strength, Sun
		</DOMAIN>
		<ALIGNMENT>
			Neutral Good
		</ALIGNMENT>
		<DESCRIPTION>
			 Pelor is the god of the Sun, Light, Strength, and Healing. He is known as the Shining One, and the Sun Father. He is known as the creator of much that is good. His holy symbol is a face in a sun. A Flan deity, Pelor is worshipped throughout the Flanaess, and on other worlds as well. He rides a mighty ki-rin named Star Thought, summoning eagles and destroying evil with bolts of light. He is depicted as an older man with wild golden hair and beard, dressed in robes of shining white. Pelorians believe that the life-giving sun is the best cure for all of Oerth's ills. Justice and freedom are brought about through charity, modesty, and perseverance. Pelor's priests teach that the truly strong don't need to prove their power. Pelorians strive to perform so many good acts that evil has no room in which to exist, though they will fight if necessary. Pelor strength is a spiritual strength, opposed to physical strength like Kord. His strength is the power of will and hope, the need to face evil in the face of insurmountable odds. Pelor is wrathful against the forces of evil, corruption, and darkness, and is especially opposed to the undead. However, Pelor urges his followers to remember that excessive attention to things of evil can blind one to the truly important things: compassion and goodness.
		</DESCRIPTION>
		<FAVOREDWEAPON>Mace</FAVOREDWEAPON>
	</DEITY>
	<DEITY>
		<NAME>
			St. Cuthbert: God of Retribution
		</NAME>
		<DOMAIN>
			Destruction, Law, Protection, Strength
		</DOMAIN>
		<ALIGNMENT>
			Lawful Neutral
		</ALIGNMENT>
		<DESCRIPTION>
			Saint Cuthbert of the Cudgel is the combative deity of Wisdom, Dedication, and Zeal. Rumored to have once been a mortal man, Saint Cuthbert is an intermediate deity. His alignment has been variously interpreted as lawful neutral (lawful good tendencies) and lawful good (lawful neutral tendencies). Saint Cuthbert hates evil, but is more concerned with law and order, with converting the uninformed, and preventing backsliding among the faithful. When they shed their mortal coils, those who worshiped the saint in life go to Saint Cuthbert's divine realm, called the Basilica of Saint Cuthbert or the Bastion of Law. This realm is in Arcadia. Souls there act as silent observers while the saint gives out judgments from his Seat of Truth. Saint Cuthbert seldom leaves his plane unless some great duty calls him forth.
		</DESCRIPTION>
		<FAVOREDWEAPON>Mace</FAVOREDWEAPON>
	</DEITY>
	<DEITY>
		<NAME>
			Vecna: God of Secrets
		</NAME>
		<DOMAIN>
			Evil, Knowledge, Magic
		</DOMAIN>
		<ALIGNMENT>
			Neutral Evil
		</ALIGNMENT>
		<DESCRIPTION>
			Vecna was described as a powerful wizard who became a lich. He was eventually destroyed, and his right hand and left eye were the only parts of his body to survive. Even after he achieved godhood, he is still described as missing both his left eye and left hand. Vecna's holy symbol is an eye in the palm of a left hand. Being a secretive cult, there are no real collections of Vecnan teachings. However, copies of the Book of Vile Darkness are highly prized by the cult for Vecna's role in that work's development. The Open Grave book offers the "Scroll of Mauthereign", which offers a twisted version of Vecna's history and tells his followers that committing evil acts is a holy and righteous act.
		</DESCRIPTION>
		<FAVOREDWEAPON>Dagger</FAVOREDWEAPON>
	</DEITY>
	<DEITY>
		<NAME>
			Wee Jas: Goddess of Death and Magic
		</NAME>
		<DOMAIN>
			Death, Law, Magic
		</DOMAIN>
		<ALIGNMENT>
			Lawful Neutral
		</ALIGNMENT>
		<DESCRIPTION>
			Wee Jas is the Suel goddess of Magic, Death, Vanity, and Law. Her symbol is a skull in front of a fireball, or just a red skull. Wee Jas always appears as a highly attractive human female; other than that, details of her appearance vary wildly. Wee Jas thinks of herself as a steward of the dead. Though she is a relatively benign death goddess, she has no problem with undead being created - as long as they are not reanimated against their will, and their remains are procured in a lawful manner
		</DESCRIPTION>
		<FAVOREDWEAPON>Dagger</FAVOREDWEAPON>
	</DEITY>
	<DEITY>
		<NAME>
			Yondalla: Goddess of the Halflings
		</NAME>
		<DOMAIN>
			Lawful Good
		</DOMAIN>
		<ALIGNMENT>
			Good, Law, Protection
		</ALIGNMENT>
		<DESCRIPTION>
			Yondalla is the chief halfling goddess.  Her symbol is a shield with a cornucopia motif. Yondalla is the goddess of Protection, Fertility, the Halfling Race, Children, Security, Leadership, Diplomacy, Wisdom, the Cycle of Life, Creation, Family and Familial Love, Tradition, Community, Harmony, and Prosperity. Yondalla is also known as the Protector and the Provider, the Nurturing Matriarch, and the Blessed One. Yondalla is represented as a strong female halfling with red-golden hair, looking determined and proud. She dresses in green, yellow, and brown, and carries a shield. Yondalla has two aspects that the halflings speak of in front of others: the Provider and the Protector. As the Provider, she is a goddess of fertility and growing things, of birth and youth. She can make barren things fertile and increase the growing rate of plants and animals to any speed she chooses. She can equally easily make fertile things barren, if she chooses. She can age, wither, and slay as easily as she can create, though it takes much to drive her to do this. As Protector, Yondalla wards off evil influences and intrusions and gives halflings the strength and determination to defend themselves. In this aspect, Yondalla most often uses her illusionist abilities to protect her worshippers.
		</DESCRIPTION>
		<FAVOREDWEAPON>Short Sword</FAVOREDWEAPON>
	</DEITY>
</DEITIES>