<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<RACES>
	<RACE>
		<NAME>
			HUMAN
		</NAME>
		<DESCRIPTION>
		</DESCRIPTION>
		<SPECIALABILITIES>

		</SPECIALABILITIES>
		<ABILITYADJ>
			0, 0, 0, 0, 0, 0
		</ABILITYADJ>
		<FAVCLASS>
			Any. When determining whether a multiclass human takes an experience point penalty, his or her highest-level class does not count.
		</FAVCLASS>
		<SIZE>
			Medium: As Medium creatures, humans have no special bonuses or penalties due to their size. 
		</SIZE>
		<SPEED>
			Human base land speed is 30 feet. 
		</SPEED>
		<TRAITS>
			1 extra feat at 1st level.
			4 extra skill points at 1st level and 1 extra skill point at each additional level.
		</TRAITS>
		<SKILLCHECKADJ>
		</SKILLCHECKADJ>
		<AUTOMATICLANGUAGES>
			Common
		</AUTOMATICLANGUAGES>
		<BONUSLANGUAGES>
			Any (other than secret languages such as Druidic) 
		</BONUSLANGUAGES>
	</RACE>
	<RACE>
		<NAME>
			DWARF
		</NAME>
		<DESCRIPTION>
		</DESCRIPTION>
		<SPECIALABILITIES>
			Darkvision, Stonecunning, Weapon Familiarity(Dwarven Waraxe), Weapon Familiarity(Dwarven Urgrosh), Stability
		</SPECIALABILITIES>
		<ABILITYADJ>
			0, 0, 2, 0, 0, -2
		</ABILITYADJ>
		<FAVCLASS>
			Fighter. A multiclass dwarf 's fighter class does not count when determining whether he takes an experience point penalty for multiclassing
		</FAVCLASS>
		<SIZE>
			Medium: As Medium creatures, dwarves have no special bonuses or penalties due to their size.
		</SIZE>
		<SPEED>
			Dwarf base land speed is 20 feet. However, dwarves can move at this speed even when wearing medium or heavy armor or when carrying a medium or heavy load (unlike other creatures, whose speed is reduced in such situations).
		</SPEED>
		<TRAITS>
		</TRAITS>
		<SKILLCHECKADJ>
			+2 racial bonus on saving throws against poison.
			+2 racial bonus on saving throws against spells and spell-like effects.
			+1 racial bonus on attack rolls against orcs and goblinoids.
			+4 dodge bonus to Armor Class against monsters of the giant type. Any time a creature loses its Dexterity bonus (if any) to Armor Class, such as when it's caught flat-footed, it loses its dodge bonus, too.
			+2 racial bonus on Appraise checks that are related to stone or metal items.
			+2 racial bonus on Craft checks that are related to stone or metal.
		</SKILLCHECKADJ>
		<AUTOMATICLANGUAGES>
			Common, Dwarven
		</AUTOMATICLANGUAGES>
		<BONUSLANGUAGES>
			Giant, Gnome, Goblin, Orc, Terran, Undercommon
		</BONUSLANGUAGES>
	</RACE>
	<RACE>
		<NAME>
			ELF
		</NAME>
		<DESCRIPTION>
			Immunity to magic sleep effects, and a +2 racial saving throw bonus against enchantment spells or effects.
		</DESCRIPTION>
		<SPECIALABILITIES>
			Low-Light Vision, Weapon Proficiency (Longbow), Weapon Proficiency (Shortbow), Weapon Proficiency (Longsword), Weapon Proficiency (Rapier)
		</SPECIALABILITIES>
		<ABILITYADJ>
			0, 2, -2, 0, 0, 0
		</ABILITYADJ>
		<FAVCLASS>
			Fighter. A multiclass dwarf 's fighter class does not count when determining whether he takes an experience point penalty for multiclassing
		</FAVCLASS>
		<SIZE>
			Medium: As Medium creatures, dwarves have no special bonuses or penalties due to their size.
		</SIZE>
		<SPEED>
			Elf base land speed is 30 feet.
		</SPEED>
		<TRAITS>
		</TRAITS>
		<SKILLCHECKADJ>
			+2 racial bonus on Listen, Search, and Spot checks. An elf who merely passes within 5 feet of a secret or concealed door is entitled to a Search check to notice it as if she were actively looking for it.
		</SKILLCHECKADJ>
		<AUTOMATICLANGUAGES>
			Common, Dwarven
		</AUTOMATICLANGUAGES>
		<BONUSLANGUAGES>
			Giant, Gnome, Goblin, Orc, Terran, Undercommon
		</BONUSLANGUAGES>
	</RACE>
	<RACE>
		<NAME>
			GNOME
		</NAME>
		<DESCRIPTION>
		</DESCRIPTION>
		<SPECIALABILITIES>
			Low-Light Vision, Weapon Familiarity (Gnome Hooked Hammer)
		</SPECIALABILITIES>
		<ABILITYADJ>
			-2, 0, 2, 0, 0, 0
		</ABILITYADJ>
		<FAVCLASS>
			Bard. A multiclass gnome's bard class does not count when determining whether he takes an experience point penalty.
		</FAVCLASS>
		<SIZE>
			Small: As a Small creature, a gnome gains a +1 size bonus to Armor Class, a +1 size bonus on attack rolls, and a +4 size bonus on Hide checks, but he uses smaller weapons than humans use, and his lifting and carrying limits are three-quarters of those of a Medium character.
		</SIZE>
		<SPEED>
			Gnome base land speed is 20 feet.
		</SPEED>
		<TRAITS>
			Spell-Like Abilities: 1/day-speak with animals (burrowing mammal only, duration 1 minute). A gnome with a Charisma score of at least 10 also has the following spell-like abilities: 1/day-dancing lights, ghost sound, prestidigitation. Caster level 1st; save DC 10 + gnome's Cha modifier + spell level.
		</TRAITS>
		<SKILLCHECKADJ>
			+2 racial bonus on saving throws against illusions.
			Add +1 to the Difficulty Class for all saving throws against illusion spells cast by gnomes. This adjustment stacks with those from similar effects.
			+1 racial bonus on attack rolls against kobolds and goblinoids.
			+4 dodge bonus to Armor Class against monsters of the giant type. Any time a creature loses its Dexterity bonus (if any) to Armor Class, such as when it's caught flat-footed, it loses its dodge bonus, too.
			+2 racial bonus on Listen checks.
			+2 racial bonus on Craft (alchemy) checks.
		</SKILLCHECKADJ>
		<AUTOMATICLANGUAGES>
			Common, Gnome
		</AUTOMATICLANGUAGES>
		<BONUSLANGUAGES>
			Draconic, Dwarven, Elven, Giant, Goblin, Orc
		</BONUSLANGUAGES>
	</RACE>
	<RACE>
		<NAME>
			HALF-ELF
		</NAME>
		<DESCRIPTION>
			Immunity to sleep spells and similar magical effects, and a +2 racial bonus on saving throws against enchantment spells or effects.
		</DESCRIPTION>
		<SPECIALABILITIES>
			Low-Light Vision
		</SPECIALABILITIES>
		<ABILITYADJ>
			0, 0, 0, 0, 0, 0
		</ABILITYADJ>
		<FAVCLASS>
			Any. When determining whether a multiclass half-elf takes an experience point penalty, her highest-level class does not count.
		</FAVCLASS>
		<SIZE>
			Medium: As Medium creatures, half-elves have no special bonuses or penalties due to their size.
		</SIZE>
		<SPEED>
			Half-elf base land speed is 30 feet.
		</SPEED>
		<TRAITS>
			Elven Blood: For all effects related to race, a half-elf is considered an elf.
		</TRAITS>
		<SKILLCHECKADJ>
			+1 racial bonus on Listen, Search, and Spot checks.
			+2 racial bonus on Diplomacy and Gather Information checks.
		</SKILLCHECKADJ>
		<AUTOMATICLANGUAGES>
			Common, Elven
		</AUTOMATICLANGUAGES>
		<BONUSLANGUAGES>
			Any (other than secret languages such as Druidic)
		</BONUSLANGUAGES>
	</RACE>
	<RACE>
		<NAME>
			HALF-ORC
		</NAME>
		<DESCRIPTION>
		</DESCRIPTION>
		<SPECIALABILITIES>
			Darkvision
		</SPECIALABILITIES>
		<ABILITYADJ>
			2, 0, 0, -2, 0, -2
		</ABILITYADJ>
		<FAVCLASS>
			Barbarian. A multiclass half-orc's barbarian class does not count when determining whether he takes an experience point penalty.
		</FAVCLASS>
		<SIZE>
			Medium: As Medium creatures, half-orcs have no special bonuses or penalties due to their size.
		</SIZE>
		<SPEED>
			Half-orc base land speed is 30 feet.
		</SPEED>
		<TRAITS>
			A half-orc's starting Intelligence score is always at least 3. If this adjustment would lower the character's score to 1 or 2, his score is nevertheless 3.
			Orc Blood: For all effects related to race, a half-orc is considered an orc.
		</TRAITS>
		<SKILLCHECKADJ>
			+1 racial bonus on Listen, Search, and Spot checks.
			+2 racial bonus on Diplomacy and Gather Information checks.
		</SKILLCHECKADJ>
		<AUTOMATICLANGUAGES>
			Common, Orc
		</AUTOMATICLANGUAGES>
		<BONUSLANGUAGES>
			Draconic, Giant, Gnoll, Goblin, Abyssal
		</BONUSLANGUAGES>
	</RACE>
	<RACE>
		<NAME>
			HALFLING
		</NAME>
		<DESCRIPTION>
		</DESCRIPTION>
		<SPECIALABILITIES>
		</SPECIALABILITIES>
		<ABILITYADJ>
			-2, 2, 0, 0, 0, 0
		</ABILITYADJ>
		<FAVCLASS>
			Rogue. A multiclass halfling's rogue class does not count when determining whether she takes an experience point penalty for multiclassing.
		</FAVCLASS>
		<SIZE>
			Small: As a Small creature, a halfling gains a +1 size bonus to Armor Class, a +1 size bonus on attack rolls, and a +4 size bonus on Hide checks, but she uses smaller weapons than humans use, and her lifting and carrying limits are three-quarters of those of a Medium character.
		</SIZE>
		<SPEED>
			Halfling base land speed is 20 feet.
		</SPEED>
		<TRAITS>
		</TRAITS>
		<SKILLCHECKADJ>
			+2 racial bonus on Climb, Jump, and Move Silently checks.
			+1 racial bonus on all saving throws.
			+2 morale bonus on saving throws against fear: This bonus stacks with the halfling's +1 bonus on saving throws in general.
			+1 racial bonus on attack rolls with thrown weapons and slings.
			+2 racial bonus on Listen checks.
		</SKILLCHECKADJ>
		<AUTOMATICLANGUAGES>
			Common, Halfling
		</AUTOMATICLANGUAGES>
		<BONUSLANGUAGES>
			Dwarven, Elven, Gnome, Goblin, Orc
		</BONUSLANGUAGES>
	</RACE>
</RACES>